<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: blogging | Carl Nelson]]></title>
  <link href="http://carlrnelson.com/blog/categories/blogging/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://carlrnelson.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-05-01T15:23:24-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://carlrnelson.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Carl Nelson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Perfectionista]]></title>
    <link href="http://carlrnelson.com/blog/2012/12/08/perfectionista/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-08T17:24:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://carlrnelson.com/blog/2012/12/08/perfectionista</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the things I battle with constantly is the blank page, the emptry screen. That's why it took me so long to just suck it up and put up this writing space that isn't perfect; that isn't how I want it to be yet functions as a minimum viable experience for my writing.</p>

<p>It's easy to get sucked into learning a new tool, trying out a different setup, or avoiding the page all together than just putting fingers to the keys and writing. It's hard enough to keep all of the distractions of the world away when we need to work, no less the internal distractions that draw us away from work with promises of a better pencil. <em>Your fucking Conderoga is going to do just fine.</em></p>

<p>I've been listened to Mule Radio's show <a href="http://muleradio.net/mistakes/" title="Let's Make Mistakes">"Let's Make Mistakes"</a> with <a href="http://twitter.com/Mike_FTW" title="Mike Monteiro on Twitter">Mike Monteiro</a> and <a href="http://twitter.com/ohheygreat" title="Leah Reich on Twitter">Leah Reich</a> a lot lately. Granted that's partly because it has been pouring in San Francisco pretty much everyday for the past week and my bicycle has been in some state of disassembly, but also because it's a great show. In "Digging Yourself Out Of A Hole" and "What Happens When You Make A Mistake" they pull out some of the hard realities of creative work that we get stuck in.</p>

<h3>Digging yourself out of a hole... getting stuck and what to do.</h3>

<p>I found myself this week in a hole. I was coming back to the designs for a project at work that has been a long time going. And just to put it into context, this project isn't a sexy project; it's the sweaty, roll up your sleeves and get it done kind of project. So, I'm coming back to this project for which I had already built out a functional prototype during our last dev release cycle and some additional robustness that I'd been arguing for got scoped in, yet I'm stuck in the under-scoped unreleased prototype design and just can't get it moving again.</p>

<p>This is what Mike loosely explained as the <em>"it's 3pm and the designer is still only on version 3 of the mockup"</em> problem. I was waiting for that idea to be <strong>The Idea</strong>, and so when I went back, that idea was what I latched onto and it wasn't getting me anywhere. I expected it to be the solution and it wasn't. Cue my exceptional design director to come into our 1 on 1 get me to question the fundamentals I had assumed for the problem. In the last hour of the day I was back on track dumping some of my assumptions and moving the work forward.</p>

<p>My design director gave me a moment to break my head above the trees and see the forest. There won't always be someone there to give me a boost above the trees but I can learn to remember to make sure to step up and take a look myself from time to time.</p>

<h3>Design as communication.</h3>

<p>If you've read <a href="http://abookapart.com/products/design-is-a-job" title="A Book Apart: Design is a Job"><em>Design is a Job</em></a> you'll know that a large part of design work is about selling your work, essentially a communication tool. If you haven't read it, go... buy it, read it now.</p>

<p>Going back to the work I was doing for this project, I was stuck on it, but what I was stuck on it because I already had this communication tool that I thought was sufficient with a few tweaks, however it wasn't sufficient because my audience had changed. I had been using the prototype to test with users, to check usefulness and discover problems with usability; but now I had to communicate internally, about what we were exactly building, how it was going to work, and why we were doing it a certain way.</p>

<p>In essence, I had ended up in a different forest and I hadn't even noticed because the trees looked the same.</p>

<p>I needed to communicate with different deliverables because I was no longer talking to users, I was talking to product management and lead developers. Shifting from working within small startups where there is no product management structure and what you're designing is getting built the same week to a large organization where a large part of the design process is creating documentation of your work is still a challenge for me. Those documents help you sell you ideas when you aren't there, they also make sure your ideas are clearly documented when the building happens, or when questions arise as to how things will be built.</p>

<p>The urge to build first can get in the way of communicating your ideas to larger audiences outside of your immediate team, so don't shy away from deliverables that are communication tools first.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Octopress]]></title>
    <link href="http://carlrnelson.com/blog/2012/11/22/octopress/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-22T20:17:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://carlrnelson.com/blog/2012/11/22/octopress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the start of working in markdown again.</p>

<p>Brings me back to the days where I wrote .php files and uploaded them to a folder and a php script continually displayed the latest in the list.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
