<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: life | Carl Nelson]]></title>
  <link href="http://carlrnelson.com/blog/categories/life/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://carlrnelson.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-05-01T15:23:24-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://carlrnelson.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Carl Nelson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Creative Method]]></title>
    <link href="http://carlrnelson.com/blog/2013/09/18/creative-method/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-18T16:50:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://carlrnelson.com/blog/2013/09/18/creative-method</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It's been 230 days (or so) since my last post and looking back at my <a href="http://www.carlrnelson.com/blog/2013/01/30/2013-ahead/">2013 Ahead</a> I feel like I've done a decent job with some of the things on that list, minus the utter lack of writing that has occurred. And while the last seven months have been creative and good, they have felt scattered and unfocused in some ways. I've been lacking a system of organization even though I haven't missed the lack of one, until recently.</p>

<p>I started reading the book <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Making-Ideas-Happen-Overcoming-ebook/dp/B003NX75W2/">Making Ideas Happen</a> by Scott Belsky, the founder of the Behance network and the creator of the Action Method, and started mulling over my lack of creative method. While not an egregious omission from my life, I imagine it keeps me from really tackling all of the things that need to get done in an effective and efficient manner.</p>

<p>With that in mind, I've taken it upon myself to piece my own Creative Method together using tools I like and some systems that work for other people.</p>

<h2>A creative method in four parts.</h2>

<h3>Part One - Action Items</h3>

<p>The central part of the Action Method is the Action Item: a discrete, actionable <em>(get it?)</em> piece of work that can be captured and checked off.</p>

<p>The Action Item is what drives work forward; if you can’t act on something, it’s just going to languish and never get done. It helps you to break work into discrete pieces that you can finish.</p>

<h3>Part Two - Evernote</h3>

<p>I’ve used Evernote in the past to capture notes <em>(surprised, right?)</em>, images of white boarding sessions and sketches, and even to outline ideas for writing. However, I hadn’t though to use it as an organizational system until I read <a href="http://alistapart.com/article/connected-ux">Connected UX</a> and combined it with pieces of the Action Method from Making Ideas Happen.</p>

<p>It has everything that I need: tags, search, notes, photo capturing, memos. It’s a great place to store references, clip websites and articles, capture notes, create to-do lists, but most importantly to create a structured set of tags and searchable metadata around pieces of information.</p>

<p>Most to-do list applications, including the Action Method app, eventually fell by the wayside, replaced by sticky note to-do lists plastering the edges of my monitor, because they weren’t connected to the rest of the information I needed. Evernote gave me the perfect combination of unstructured data input with structured metadata that I could then query and act on.</p>

<h3>Part Three - Daily Planning</h3>

<p>It’s easy to get into the office in the morning and get swept up in the bustling web of email, social networks, and meetings without even a nod to what you need to tackle that day. I’ve lost a lot of days to these kinds of mornings <em>(including today)</em> and they suck. They are hard to recover from without resetting your day somehow <em>(hitting the gym is usually my only good reset button)</em>.</p>

<p>Out of this planning wasteland were born my morning planning sessions. The first thing I do is sit down at my desk and go through my action items. I select a couple of high priority ones that will take dedicated time, often more involved design or analysis tasks. Also immediately tackling a few quick-to-knock-off action items, usually email followups or planning items. I’ll also quickly triage my email if I have time, create follow-up action items and get moving on my day.</p>

<h3>Part Four - Daily Retro</h3>

<p>I took this idea from our agile practice at work but compressed it to a daily practice. It’s a quick look at what went well, what didn’t go well, and what I should think about changing. It’s bit of a reflective +/-/Δ moment where I try to understand how my day went.</p>

<p>I also use this time to add any end of day action items that I’ve jotted down on paper throughout the day that haven’t made it into Evernote yet.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Creative Spaces]]></title>
    <link href="http://carlrnelson.com/blog/2013/02/25/creative-spaces/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-25T19:43:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://carlrnelson.com/blog/2013/02/25/creative-spaces</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I finally purchased a desk. After tormenting myself with the dreamy fields of vintage and high-end designer desks. I stumbled across a desk at Scandanavian Designs that was very nearly exactly what I was looking for. So much so that it parallelled some of the design decisions I made while sketching an ideal desk.</p>

<p>And so the first pieces of my creative workspace are coming together. The desk is the keystone. The rest layers atop of it.</p>

<p>It makes such a difference to have a workspace all your own. A place where you can feel free to leave work in progress scattered across the surface to come back to the next day. A place you can paste up crazy ideas. A place where hours whisk away as you begin researching a new project.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2013 Ahead]]></title>
    <link href="http://carlrnelson.com/blog/2013/01/30/2013-ahead/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-30T14:23:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://carlrnelson.com/blog/2013/01/30/2013-ahead</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>2013 is already a promising year. Nicole and I just moved into an <a class="fancybox" href="../images/assets/new_apartment_2013.jpg" title="Our Amazing Loft">amazing apartment</a> which we're excited to make our own. Especially exciting is creating a workspace where my creative projects can live. I'm booked to teach two dance events this year and the dance troupe is rolling along with our choreography for ILHC. There is a lot I would like to get to this year, and even if I don't or if my ideas change partway through the year, that's okay.</p>

<p>Below are some vaguely sweeping themes for 2013. They are followed by some more specific intentions constrained to the first quarter of the year.</p>

<h2>Themes of 2013</h2>

<h4>Making &amp; Craftsmanship</h4>

<p>I'm looking forward to creating as a big part of 2013. The first part of that will be fashioning a workspace. From there I'll hopefully litter the space with sketches, schematics, code, writings, and possibly even some physical projects including arduiono systems. I get so very excited when I have the chance to actually spend time working with my hands and the only way to get better at my craft is to put in the time and work.</p>

<h4>Reading &amp; Mental Exploration</h4>

<p>One of the greatest ways for me to break out of my own ideas and perspective is to surround myself in the words and thoughts of someone else. I aim to spend more time reading, digesting and exploring the mental spaces of others. Whether that is through finding possibilities in fiction, deepening my understanding of scientific or technical realms, or drifting through visual spaces with art, architecture and design books.</p>

<h2>Next 3 Months</h2>

<h4>Creative Workspace</h4>

<p>Create a space where I feel comfortable tinkering, sketching, floating amongst my own ideas. Invest time in designing how that space is going to feel; how it is going encourage me to create; how it will enhance how and why I work. To not feel constrained by its prettiness or acceptability. To feel free in that space to start in on the daunting blank canvas and to leave work out, rough edges and all that will tease at me to finish them.</p>

<h4>RWS Downtime</h4>

<p>RWS will stand as shorthand for read, write or sketch. In my downtown, rather than spend time on social networks, checking email or watching videos, I'll spend it either reading, writing, or sketching. In this way I'll be working within one of my two themes for the year, but also engaging in a different way with my idle time.</p>

<h4>Find A Design Mentor</h4>

<p>One of the things I learned over the last year working with athletic coaches was that having someone there to observe, give feedback, and push you past your current limits. I want to find and develop a relationship with a designer locally to give me those same kinds of nudges and feedback as a designer. Part of that will be connecting with a lot of more senior designers who are working in spaces I find interesting, the rest will be a work in progress.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2012 Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://carlrnelson.com/blog/2013/01/03/2012-review/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-03T12:10:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://carlrnelson.com/blog/2013/01/03/2012-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>2012 was an exceptional year. For oh so many reasons it has turned out to be one of my favorites so far. The short of it is that I feel that I have finally gotten a grasp on what it means to be me in the context of a relatively high functioning adult. I have vaulted into a career that I'm exceptionally happy with. I'm in a preposterously amazing relationship that continues to grow and amaze me with the wonderful <a href="http://www.nicolezuckerman.com" title="Nicole Zuckerman's website">Nicole Zuckerman</a>. I have finally stepped up and taken responsibility for adult things, e.g. the dreaded realm of finances. 2012 was a year when things worked out amazingly, when Obama got re-elected, and when I was stupid and <a href="http://astudyinmovement.com/post/30464236368/thats-my-fractured-finger-woo" title="Yep that's a fracture">broke my middle finger</a> finger-wrestling.</p>

<h2>Professional 2012</h2>

<h4>Salesforce.com</h4>

<p>I started at Salesforce as a Senior UI Designer in April 2012. They reached out to me, which felt amazing, and I couldn't be happier to be with them this year. I've learned an exceptional amount as a designer, a communicator, and a person working within a large company alongside exceptionally talented designers and researchers. The work is challenging in both complexity and scope, yet I have the time and support to pursue deepening my knowledge taking classes and going to conferences. My process is richer for the time I have spent here so far and I can't wait for another year.</p>

<h4>Speaking &amp; Teaching</h4>

<p>This year I was asked to speak on a panel at the Enterprise 2.0 Conference down in San Jose. In doing so I had a blast evangelizing design and cracking some carapaces at <a href="http://www.theboilingcrab.com/" title="The Boiling Crab Restaurant">The Boiling Crab</a> with other designers. Design is going to be a strong field within enterprise as users become more savvy with technology and their expectations increase. I also taught four <a href="http://www.skillshare.com">Skillshare</a> this year. Two on my own on <a href="http://www.skillshare.com/UX-Flows-Beyond-Sitemaps-and-Wireframes/960131487">UX Flows</a> and two with <a href="https://twitter.com/robsurrency">Rob Surrency</a> and <a href="http://twitter.com/#!/jonathanhung">Jonathan Hung</a> on <a href="http://www.skillshare.com/Guiding-UX-Principles-Extended/1032532550">Guiding UX Principles</a>. I've always found teaching to be a way to learn more about a craft and I love sharing the knowledge I have with others.</p>

<h4>JavaScript &amp; Coding</h4>

<p>I've spent more time this year deepening my knowledge of JavaScript and programming in general. In part thanks to the courses available to me through work, but also independently. Rather than relying heavily on frameworks while not understanding what is going on underneath the hood as I have mostly done in the past, I spent many hours writing in pure JavaScript. I finally grasped the concept of closure, that was a good one. And, I have spent time thinking about code on a more abstract scale when working rather than just diving in and writing.</p>

<h2>Personal 2012</h2>

<h4>Love &amp; Friendship</h4>

<p>This year I spent so much wonderful time deepening my relationship with Nicole. We've danced a lot more together. We've planned more together. We support each other through and through while encouraging each other to grow in the ways we want to see ourselves. We continue to love each other more and more. We're tackling a life together. <a class="fancybox" href="../images/assets/carl_nicole_nye_2012.jpg" title="Carl and Nicole on New Year's Eve 2012">This photo says it all</a>. Additionally, I've tried to make an effort to spend more time connecting with my parents and sister including skype calls and more time in person. I didn't do as good of a job staying connected with some of my good friends who are elsewhere this year, despite managing the occasional visit or Skype call, and hope to make a better stab at that next year.</p>

<h4>Dance</h4>

<p>I spent less time dancing overall this year than I have in years past. Part of this was confronting the realization that I wasn't getting what I wanted out of dancing. I crossed into eleven years of dancing and my goals and priorities have changed considerably over the last couple of years. I'm no longer interested in traveling, teaching and competing all of the time. I enjoy those activities but it wasn't fruitful for me, I wasn't as engaged with the dance as I tried those things I had been doing. A lot of the year was spent with some frustration around dance. Even with the great advice from peers whose advice I value, it took me most of the year to start finding delight in the dance again. Part of it comes back to exploring new parts of the dance that I haven't, such as balboa, and the other part comes back to digging into a part of the dance I haven't done in a while. Choreography. I started choregraphing a group piece in the fall, and also helped choreograph <a href="http://goo.gl/LiC6U" title="Carl &amp; Nicole 30 Second Showcase">two other</a> pieces this year.</p>

<h4>Money</h4>

<p>I've never been a big fan of dealing with money, but this year I got a hold of my shit and started making sure of my financial life was in order. I made sure my credit card debt was all gone and paid off large portions of some personal debt. I took over some student loan payments from my parents. I got a 401k plan and started making sure part of my paycheck went into a savings account (it helps that I have a nice job at Salesforce now). I have health insurance and made use of it (particularly for that broken finger). All in all, a good year for my financial responsibilities.</p>

<h4>Health &amp; Movement</h4>

<p>I joined a <a href="http://studiomix.com">gym</a> that I think is awesome this year. It's a great space where I feel not only comfortable to go and work out in, but also to go and hang out in the cafe. I know the staff well and I appreciate their attitude of a physical culture. I've also started worked with two trainers this year. Kirk has improved my skills with kettlebells and reconnected me with pilates. Vincent has helped me with gymnastic training and I've had massive progress on the rings, in my floor work and my handstand. I'm very excited that I've seen so much progress with not only my strength and mental mindset but also in the development of a physical skillset that I've always wanted to work more on.</p>

<p>When it comes to the health side of things, I've notably drank less this year than in prior years and am generally trying to make a mental effort to not drink as much alcohol. I'm also trying to imbibe less coffee (and in turn more tea and water) during the day at work, although depending on the day it's a battle I'm willing to lose once in a while. I haven't been as vigilant about what I'm eating and I feel that I could use more vegetables in my diet.</p>

<h4>Skills</h4>

<p>This year I spent time investing in some other various skills I wasn't anticipating learning more about. I got CPR and Emergency Response certified through a program at work. It's the second time I've been certified and it feels good to know I can help someone in need. I also spent a lot of time learning more about bike repair and maintenance as I purchase a less-than-complete bicycle off of Craigslist and it has become an occasionally tedious but educational experience. Lastly, I purchased a Sony NEX-7. One of the prosumer mirrorless DSLRs and have been taking pictures incessantly with it. In the six or so months I've had it, I can see a visible improvement in my ability to see and frame a shot, although I'm still not always getting the shot I want. I even printed one of my photos in large format for my mother for Christmas.</p>

<h4>Writing</h4>

<p>Lastly, I've been shit at writing this year. It just hasn't been on my priority list and I have felt hampered by not having a good workspace to sit and write when I'm at home. I think writing really helps change the way I look at the world, it changes my perspective when I might write about what I'm doing or seeing. The bit of writing that I've been decent at this year was responding to my OhLife emails which come in daily and remind me to journal just a little bit.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
